Mark Maglana

Software Engineer with Twist of DevOps

(925) 558-5456 mark@maglana.com https://relaxdiego.com SF Bay Area, CA

I am a software engineer who has been in the DevOps world since 2008 contributing my knowledge on sound software development practices to my Ops colleagues. Likewise, I have been contributing what I learn from Ops to my Dev colleagues. I enjoy what I do not only because I get to learn new things and practice them everyday but also because I get to impart them to my colleagues on both sides.

Accomplishments

- Increased Billing Component Accuracy and Speed by at Least 10x I offered to re-design and reimplement a cloud computing application's billing module which was producing incomplete results and regularly timing out before it could even display half of an account's report. After the redesign, the reports were displayed immediately, and the amounts were 100% accurate.
- Facilitated Timely Delivery of Software By Automating Requirements My employer needed to deliver an autonomous software agent for a customer. I offered to study the associated open standards and proprietary protocols to learn about the complete requirements. I then codified these requirements in an application that developers can execute against their code to give them instant feedback. The application later also served as a regression test harness allowing the team to deliver the software on time and within budget.
- Was Into Containerization Before It Was Cool! I have been following containerization since the initial Docker days even though it was outside my assignment. Because of my skunkworks preparation, I was able to build an Ansible-based project that provisioned an HA OpenShift environment as a means to replace our internal CI/CD pipeline.
- Reduced a 2-day Manual Process to 5-seconds While building the MIS for a metal fabrication shop, I learned about a manual computation process that took shop floor engineers 2 days to complete. After some research and a few questions on a compsci newsgroup, I was able to build a desktop app that reduced the computation time to 5 seconds.
- Improved Requirements Gathering Through Prototyping Upon joining a new software consulting firm, I noticed the long feedback loop from requirements gathering to user testing. I encouraged and guided my teammates to adopt prototyping as one of the ways to improve requirements gathering and reduce waste. The results were positive and the engineers along with the users were very happy with the results.

• Recipient of Academic Excellence Award for Best Strategic Plan - I wanted to understand the business of software and decided that focusing on the basics of business management was key. I then applied for our state university's graduate program for management where I was accepted. During the program, I was top of class for Operations Management, Financial Management, and Business Strategy. I then used everything that I learned to create a strategic plan for our family business which resulted in me getting the strategic plan award.

A Few Open Source Projects

- **Open vSwitch Lab** A Vagrant project that provisions two machines that talk over a simulated Internet. The lab is a companion project for the series of articles I wrote about VXLAN, OVSDB, and the hardware VTEP schema. Source in Github.
- Aviator A lightweight Ruby client library for cloud REST APIs. I initially built this for the OpenStack API. My focus was to build a library that reflected, rather than obscured the underlying API. Homepage.
- Mana Mana A proof-of-concept business natural language testing framework that was inspired by Cucumber and the Robot framework. This was borne of my never-ending search for better ways to write maintainable automated tests. Source in Github.

One More Thing

Coding without tests is like driving a Tesla in ludicrous mode **without seatbelts** so I always make sure to cover my code with a reasonable amount of tests. Here's how I work.

Experience

Software/DevOps Engineer (Jan 2014 - Sep 2016)

Dimension Data, Pleasanton, CA

Dimension Data is a leading provider of professional, cloud, consulting and managed services for advanced IT solutions. Our team actively contributed to Ansible, OpenStack, Open vSwitch, and Open DayLight. My official title was QA/Release Engineer but my responsibilities spanned way beyond that and I happily took on every assignment sent my way!

- Wrote Ansible modules to be used for provisioning resources on Dimension Data's cloud service.
- Developed an Ansible-based project that deployed an HA OpenShift platform for use by our team as a replacement for our CI/CD pipeline.
- Designed and implemented the full stack for a web application that was designed to transform data from one format to another.

- Designed and implemented an automated test harness framework used by our testers for our various software products.
- Mentored development teams in new technologies, standards, and even 3rd-party protocols that they needed to incorporate or interface to. This allowed them to hit the ground running and deliver within budget.

Software/DevOps Engineer (Jul 2012 - Jan 2014)

Morph, Manhattan Beach, CA

Morph produced IaaS appliances that its customers can install inside of their data center to use as a springboard for quickly building their own cloud computing environment. My official title was Senior Director of Engineering but my actual roles spanned that of a software engineer.

- Designed and developed a billing module for the product.
- Wrote a Ruby client library for the OpenStack API.
- Wrote a Cucumber-based integration test for the QA team.
- Mentored developers on proper software development practices.
- Helped set up the CI tools and process to ensure the main branch always has deployable, stable code.

Software Product Manager (Jan 2008 - Jul 2012)

Exist Global, Manila, Philippines

Exist provides tailored solutions, consulting and full cycle IT services to customers around the globe. At the time, I was assigned to Morph to help produce its cloud computing product.

- Oversaw the design and implementation of Morph AppSpace, one of the earliest Platform-as-a-Service providers built on top of AWS in the market.
- Managed the product roadmap to ensure that requirements are prioritized properly and that they contain the right information.
- I helped Marketing Communications in their effort to generate product information for various marketing collateral.
- Implemented agile practices in Engineering to ensure timely delivery of stories and an overall coordinated effort of releases.

Systems Analyst/Programmer (Mar 2003 - Dec 2006)

Deco Machine Shop, Davao City, Philippines

Deco Machine Shop, Inc. provides industrial machine fabrication services nationwide. Its major clients include Dole Philippines and San Miguel Corporation. As a systems analyst, my job was to understand

the processes of the company and build software tools to automate parts of it. Software tools developed include a gear combination application which reduced a machinist's work from one day to just under 5 seconds while increasing work precision.

In 2007, I took a year off to obtain my second Master's degree.

Systems Analyst/Programmer (Jan 2002 - Jan 2003)

iThink Technologies, Davao City, Philippines

iThink provides business software and training solutions for major companies nationwide. Major clients include the Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas, Meralco, and Davao Light and Power Company. I was involved as a systems analyst/programmer for the development of purchasing systems, HR systems, and other enterprise applications for iThink's major customers. I also spearheaded the use of the Unified Modeling Language within the company and also provided some in-house training for a number of then upcoming technologies and development platforms.

Web Developer (Jan 2001 - Jan 2002)

Smartweb Philippines, Cebu City, Philippines

Smartweb was a US-based company with its production facility based in Cebu. It was involved in developing websites for small to medium sized businesses in the USA. I was a team leader in this organization. Apart from this, I also developed Smartweb's employee time tracking and billing system, which later helped speed up the invoicing and employee time tracking for the company.

Student Volunteer - Web Developer (Jun 1997 - Oct 2000)

University of San Carlos, Cebu City, Philippines

While attending college I was also a volunteer of the University of San Carlos Web Development Team which was tasked to build and maintain the university's website. I was involved in the implementation in both the client side and the server side of the website and was later promoted to team leader. The team was, by then, composed of 10 student volunteers.

Education

Master of Management, Technology, Innovation, and Commercialization

Jan 2007 - Dec 2007 The Australian National University Acton, Canberra ACT 2601, Australia

Master of Management

May 2004 - Apr 2006 University of the Philippines - School of Management Mintal, Davao City 8022, Philippines

BS Computer Engineering Jun 1995 - Oct 2000

University of San Carlos P. del Rosario Street, Cebu City 6000, Philippines

LinkedIn Recommendations

Mark is an exceptional employee from his personal interactions with his peers, development skills and passion for quality. Mark has a wide breadth of exposure to different programming languages, configuration management and software design and architecture.

— Mike Outland, DevOps Manager

Mark is an exceptionally capable software architect and developer. When a new technology or language needed to be implemented, Mark was able to obtain a deep level of understanding in a very short amount of time. I have seen him architect and implement everything from full APIs to cloud middleware to full front-ends. Over the years he has gained a wide breadth of knowledge in everything cloud & container. Working with him has been regularly humbling and wonderfully educational. Beyond his technical prowess, Mark is also very fun to work with and mentors people exceptionally well. He uses his great sense of humor to take the stress out of tough challenges and motivate teams to push on. I give Mark my highest recommendation to anything he wants to take on. He will be a rare gift to the next company he works with.

— Aimon Bustardo, DevOps Engineer

Possibly the best reason i looked forward to go to work everyday at Dimension Data is because of the opportunity to work closely and be mentored by Mark. I see him as a true software craftsman who is passionate about code and cares a lot about code quality, readability and testability. He can lead teams, mentor teammates, commit production code within time and budget while giving a helping hand with whatever is the issue of the day.

— Bert Diwa, Sr. QA Engineer

[Mark] produced solid designs. He was an expert at Python (and apparently Ruby too). He seemed to know about every Open Source project out there. His mastery of all things Git and GitHub were critical support to several of us who had never used Git before. All in all, Mark was an invaluable resource to the project and to the team. He seemed to get his dozen projects done in time while simultaneously providing whatever technical support was being asked of him by the team.

— Jay Riddell, Sr. Software Engineer

Mark was a particularly able and focused student, capable of working independently and evaluating ideas and approaches critically. His particular interest at the time was the role, design and development of business incubators as a tool for regional development.

— Don Scott-Kemmis, Professor

Misc.

This resume is available at https://www.relaxdiego.com/resume. Its source code is at https://raw.githubusercontent.com/relaxdiego/relaxdiego.github.com/master/resume/resume.adoc while the PDF format is at https://www.relaxdiego.com/resume.pdf